（アリーシャ）スレイ
Sorey...
（アリーシャ）あなたは 導師か？
Are you the Shepherd?
俺は ただの人間だよ
I'm just an ordinary human.
Not a Shepherd?
（アリーシャ）導師ではない… と
（スレイ）うん
You're human too, right?
君も 人間だよね？
This is the first time a human's ever come up here.
ここに 人間が訪れるなんて
初めてだよ
なら ここは 天の都と
呼ばれている神殿なのだろう？
In that case, this must be the Celestial Capital, right?
そうだよ
（アリーシャ）ならば 導師が…
Yeah, it is.
So shouldn't there be a Shepherd here?
導師がいるのではないか？
Not that I know of.
誰もいなかった
But I did find a mural of the
Shepherd with the Sacred Blade.
でも 壁画は見つけたよ
聖剣を掲げる導師の
A mural?
（アリーシャ）壁画…
Were the stories just old fairy tales, then?
やはり ただの伝承に
すぎなかったのか
Then the world...
もはや 世界は… 救えない
is doomed.
We'll ride upon the wind to follow
Your path leading far off into the distance
The answers we seek won't be easy to find
We set out knowing that from the start
We wander endlessly to leave behind records of our dream
It's worth it if it widens our map of the world
Resound, O song of the wind
Should we forgo sight, the voices of our hearts will push us forward
We aim always ever higher
Carry, O song of the wind
Should we go without hearing, the voices of our hearts will stream forth
Emitting a dazzling radiance
Your azure melody rings true
This is a bad idea.
（ミクリオ）まずいだろ
人間を 村に案内したら
We shouldn't bring a human to the village.
I can't just abandon someone in need.
誰であれ 困ってる人を
放っとくなんて できない
（ミクリオ）
大体 名乗らないのも変だ
Haven't you noticed that she won't even volunteer her name?
It's only natural to be cautious.
怪しいと思うのが
普通だと思うけど？
Everyone has their reasons.
事情があるんだろ
But she doesn't look like a bad person to me.
でも 悪いやつには見えない
I cannot possibly thank you enough.
スレイ 感謝する
Oh, don't mention it.
あっ いや
気にしなくていいから
ジイジのカミナリ
覚悟しておくんだね
Gramps is gonna let us have it when we get back.
Is something wrong?
（アリーシャ）何か？
（スレイ）ううん 何でもない
Nah, don't worry about it.
さっ 行こう
Well, let's get moving.
僕のことは
本当に見えてないようだね
I guess she really can't see me.
ジイジの言ったとおりだ
Just like Gramps said.
Elysia
Wow, it's beautiful.
なんという美しさだ
I half expect to see seraphim wandering around.
やはり ここは天族の…
ほんとに“天族”って呼ぶんだ
You really do call them "seraphim"!
あ… 何か おかしいだろうか？
Is that funny to you?
"Things which cannot be seen or explained,
such as gods, spirits, or supernatural phenomena,
“神 霊 魑魅魍魎(ちみもうりょう)といった
姿なき超常存在を―”
“人は 畏敬の念を込めて
天族と呼ぶ”
are revered by the people as 'seraphim.'"
Right?
でしょ？
So you've read the Celestial Record too?
（アリーシャ）君も読んだのか？
「天遺(てんい)見聞録」を
Yep. Wait, you as well?
“君も”ってことは…
Tell me, Sorey.
スレイ 教えてほしい
What's the name of your village?
君が住んでいる村は
何という村なのだ？
It's Elysia.
イズチ… だけど
Elysia?
（アリーシャ）イズチ…
I'll go report this to Gramps.
ジイジに報告してくる
Guess we can't keep quiet about this.
黙っとくわけには いかないよな
Coming by afterward?
（ミクリオ）あとで来るんだろ？
Yeah...
おっ… アハッ
Hey, everyone, I've got someone to introduce to you!
みんな 紹介する！
ここに…
Seraphim!
（アリーシャ）天族たちよ！
もし ここにいるのなら
私の話に耳を傾けてほしい
If you are here, please hear me out.
世界は 今 伝承にあるように
再び 闇に覆われようと…
Like in the legends, the world is about to be plunged into chaos.
いや すでに 闇に覆われている
No, it already is in chaos.
世界を救うには
あなたたち 天族の助けが必要だ！
We need the seraphim to restore balance to the world.
Please lend me your power!
どうか あなたたちの力を
貸してほしい！
Please give me a sign!
私の声に応えてほしい！
頼む 天族たちよ！
O seraphim, please!
Please respond...
どうか 応えて
Sorey...
（ロロ）スレイ 禍(わざわい)を招く前に
出ていってもらうんだ
Ask her to leave before she invites calamity.
You idiots!
（ジイジ）このバカモンが！
How could you bring a human into our domain?
（ジイジ）なぜ 人間を
我らの地に連れ込んだ！
Easy, Gramps.
ジイジ スレイの言い分も聞くって
言ったじゃないですか
Didn't you say you'd listen to Sorey's side of the story too?
Sorey...
（ジイジ）スレイや
You know full well the rules.
How could you break them like this?
分かっていながら
なぜ 戒めを破った？
I'm sorry, Gramps, but I couldn't just leave her there.
（スレイ）どうしても
放っておけなかったんだ
（ジイジ）うーむ
What you've already done cannot be undone.
連れてきてしまったものは
致し方ない
However, you must send her back to the realm below at once.
じゃが 今すぐ
人間を下界に退かせよ
Our priority is the peace of Elysia.
皆の平和な暮らしのためにもな
Her kind is sure to bring nothing but trouble to our domain.
この地に
禍をもたらすだけだ 人間は
But... I'm "her kind" too, you know.
俺も 人間だよ
You were raised along with our kind,
お前は わしらと共に
暮らしてきたことで―
わしらの存在を捉え
言葉を交わす力を育んだ
which nurtured in you the ability to perceive us and converse with us.
Normal humans have no such capacity.
普通の人間には できぬことじゃ
この大きな違いが
分からぬお前ではないだろう
You should understand that more than anyone else.
Then...
（スレイ）
なら どうして ジイジは―
Why did you let me have the Celestial Record, Gramps?
俺に「天遺見聞録」を
渡したのさ？
What?
なに？
本には書いてあった
It was written in the book...
ずっと前 天族と人間が
仲よく暮らしてたって―
Long ago, humans and seraphim coexisted.
I read it!
そう書いてあった
Times have changed.
（ジイジ）
その頃と 今とでは…
But she believes in the seraphim.
それに 彼女は
天族を信じてるんだ
（ジイジ）うーむ…
I must've thrown you for a loop earlier.
（アリーシャ）
昼間は 驚かせてしまったな
（アリーシャ）いるはずもない
天族に話しかけるとは―
When I spoke out to seraphim who
couldn't possibly exist. I wasn't myself.
私も どうかしていた
Oh, not at all.
ああ… いや
君が住んでる所って どんなとこ？
So then, what's your hometown like?
I'm from the capital.
（アリーシャ）都
（スレイ）みやこ？
The capital?
ハイランドの都 レディレイク
Of the Kingdom of Hyland.
Ladylake.
Ladylake?
レディレイク… って―
Like in the legend of the Sacred Blade?!
聖剣伝承が残ってる場所だよね？
"The Lady of the Lake guards the Sacred Blade, and the one who draws it becomes the Shepherd," right?
“湖の乙女の守る聖剣を
抜いた者が導師になる”って
Yes. But nobody has ever pulled the Sacred Blade out.
だけど 聖剣を抜いた者は
まだ 誰もいないんだ
（スレイ）
ミクリオ いつから？
Mikleo! How long have you been there?
Gramps sent a message.
（ミクリオ）ジイジから伝言
We do not know if the human will invite malevolence.
“いつ あの者が
穢(けが)れをもたらすか分からぬ”
But chasing her out right away is also unwise,
“しかし
いたずらに人間を追い立て―”
since that could bring forth malevolence as well.
“かえって 穢れを呼び起こして
しまうような事態は避けたい”
So...
“それゆえ
出立の支度が調うまでは 待つ”
We shall wait until she is ready to leave.
End of message.
だってさ
（スレイ）ハハッ
ありがとうって ジイジに伝えて！
Tell Gramps, "Thank you!"
あっ ミクリオも サンキュー！
And thank you, too!
I know, I know, Mikleo.
分かっておるよ ミクリオ
He means well, in all things.
あの子の気持ちは
まっすぐで 正しい
だからこそ わしは心配なのじゃ
And that's the very reason why I'm so worried for him.
Here I go.
（スレイ）いくよ
（スレイ）よし！
Got it!
あ… スレイは ずっと
このような暮らしをしているのか
Is this how you've always lived?
Yep. I've never left the village.
うん 俺
村から出たことないんだ
Sorey...
（アリーシャ）スレイ
これまで 大変な境遇だったのだな
You must've had a hard life.
What's the matter?
（スレイ）どうしたの？
（アリーシャ）いや…
I...
I can't shake the feeling that someone's watching me.
先ほどから
誰かに見られているような気が…
（スレイ）あ… 誰か―
Maybe there's someone who's worried about you.
君のことを気になってる人が
いるんじゃないかな
Yeah, right.
気を回さなくてもいい
You're trying to tell me there are seraphim, right?
天族がいると
言いたいのだろう？ 君は
（アリーシャ）ハァッ！ う…
（スレイ）あっ
ハァ… ハァ… ハァ…
落ち着いた？
Feeling better?
Thanks, I'm fine now.
すまない
もう 大丈夫だ
（スレイ）ああ よかった
Good.
（アリーシャ）「天遺見聞録」？
The Celestial Record...
Yeah.
うん 子どもの頃から
何度も読み返してるんだけど…
I've read it countless times since my childhood.
"One day, I want to explore ruins all over the world."
“いつか 世界中の遺跡を
回るのが 夢なんだ”
「天遺見聞録」を読んだ者
皆が そう言う
Everyone who's read the Celestial Record says that.
かくいう私も その１人
And I'm no exception.
But sadly...
だが 世界に 遺跡探求の
旅などという余裕はないんだ
Now is not the time for some jaunt around the world.
For several years now, the world's been plunged into a nigh-incomprehensible state of chaos.
だいぶ前から―
世界は 人智の及ばないような
災厄に見舞われている
Chaos?
（スレイ）災厄？
I experienced some of that chaos myself.
（アリーシャ）私自身―
信じられないような
おぞましい災厄に遭遇した
Chaos so horrid, I still have trouble believing it's real.
君が？
Really?
So many lives were taken right before my eyes,
including those of my friends.
私の目の前で
多くの人々の命が奪われ―
私の仲間も 命を落とした
Memories of that day are still fresh in my mind.
その光景が いまだ
私の目に焼きついている
So that's why.
だから…
“世界が闇に覆われると
いずこより現れ 光を取り戻した”
"When the world was in darkness, they appeared from the heavens and reclaimed the light."
You came here in search of the Shepherd.
君は 導師を求めて ここまで
Yes.
（アリーシャ）そうだ
The old legends were my last hope.
もはや 伝承に すがるしかないと
But now that I'm here, I know.
けれど ここへ来て分かった
伝承は 結局
おとぎ話にすぎないと
The legends are...
nothing but fairy tales.
ハァ…
（スレイ）ミクリオ！
Mikleo!
（ミクリオ）スレイ？
Sorey...
（スレイ）ミクリオ！
（ミクリオ）うわっ！
Mikleo!
I need it back right now!
頼む！ あれ 返してくれ！
Need what back?
あっ “あれ”？
This is...
これって
あっ ジイジ
Gramps!
（ジイジ）フゥ…
（スレイ）こっち こっち！
Over here!
（アリーシャ）これは…
This is...
Cool, huh?
ねっ すごいでしょ？
私も これほどのものは初めてだ
I've never seen anything like this!
Why would they create such a massive thing in the sky if it was just a fairy tale?
（スレイ）
ただの おとぎ話のために―
こんな大掛かりなものを
天空に作ったりするかな？
Not to mention the awesome temple!
しかも こんな
すっげえ神殿まで！
スレイ…
Sorey...
I found this too.
これも 一緒に見つけたんだ
The mark of the Shepherd!
導師の紋章！
（スレイ）導師は いたんだよ！
存在してたんだ！
The Shepherds did exist!
決して おとぎ話の
人物なんかじゃない！ ヘヘッ
They're not just a fairy tale!
下界が 君の言うとおり
闇に覆われようとしているなら―
If the world below is being engulfed in darkness like you say, a Shepherd will come.
導師は現れる
きっと 現れるさ
I just know it.
君は「天遺見聞録」を
信じているのだな
You really believe in the Celestial Record, don't you?
信じてる
I do.
俺の夢は
もう一度 人間と天族が―
It's my dream for humans and seraphim to coexist peacefully again.
仲よく 一緒に暮らすことなんだ
そんな世界が また 必ず
やってくるって 俺は信じてる
I really believe the world will be like that again someday.
This is for you.
これは 君に
導師は 必ず現れるから
A Shepherd will come.
Thank you, Sorey.
ありがとう スレイ
私も信じてみる
I'm going to believe too.
Someone who can draw the
Sacred Blade will come one day.
湖の乙女の守る聖剣を抜く者が
きっと現れると
ほんとに ここまででいいの？
Are you sure you'll be all right?
Yeah.
Okay.
そっか
スレイ 本当に世話になった
Sorey, thank you for everything.
アリーシャ
Alisha.
Huh?
That's my name.
（アリーシャ）
私の名は アリーシャ･ディフダ
Alisha Diphda.
You didn't even know who I was, yet you helped me without asking anything in return.
君は 何も言わずに
何者とも知れぬ私を助けてくれた
それにひきかえ 私は…
Whereas I thought only of myself.
騎士として 恥ずべきことであった
As a knight, I am ashamed.
Please find it in your heart to forgive me.
どうか 許していただきたい
（スレイ）なっ そんなこと！
It's okay, really!
（アリーシャ）もう１つ
君に謝らねばならないことがある
I must confess something to you.
イズチには 天族がいると思う
I believe that the seraphim really do exist.
Alisha...
アリーシャ
（アリーシャ）私の声には
応えてもらえなかったが―
They did not respond to my words,
but I always felt their presence around me.
いつも 姿なき存在を感じていた
To be honest, I feel them even now.
実を言うと 今も感じている
The Sacred Blade Festival is soon to commence in Ladylake.
レディレイクでは
まもなく 聖剣祭が始まる
A trial will be held based on the legend of the Shepherd's sword.
導師伝承をなぞらえた
剣の試練も行う予定だ
スレイ
Sorey...
剣の試練に挑んでみないか
Won't you take part in the trial?
Also...
それと…
やはり これは君に返しておこう
You should hold onto this.
どうして？
How come?
Yesterday, you said you wished for humans and seraphim to live together once again.
君は きのう―
人間と天族が 仲よく
一緒に暮らすことが 夢だと言った
The Shepherd I see in my mind when I read the legends...
伝承にある導師
それは きっと―
スレイ
君のような人だと思うから
I have to say,
he reminds me a lot of you.
Well, I better go.
では 行く
Sorey...
スレイ
（ジイジ）うんっ！？
（ミクリオ）ジイジ？
Gramps...
（ジイジ）何者かが
わしの領域に侵入した！
Someone has infiltrated my domain.
気配を隠したか
And they've concealed their presence.
聞け 皆の者！
Everyone, be warned!
何者かが侵入した！
There is an intruder in our realm!
おそらく 憑魔(ひょうま)じゃ！
Chance are good it's a hellion!
心して 探索にあたれ！
Search with extreme caution!
We'll go too.
俺たちも行こう！
（ミクリオ）ああ
Right!
（ルナール）クヒヒ…
Sorey!
（ミクリオ）スレイ！
（スレイ）急ごう！
Hurry!
はっ マイセン！
Mason!
（ルナール）おかしいねえ
How odd.
I didn't expect to find anything but the main course here.
（ルナール）ここには―
メインディッシュしか
ないはずなんだが―
また 新たに２人もお出ましかい
But now there're two more side dishes!
Hellion!
憑魔！
ここは 君が来るような所じゃない
This is not the place for one such as you!
Leave at once!
立ち去るんだ！
Impudent brat.
小僧が生意気に！
お前らも こいつみたいに
なりたいのか？
Do you want to end up like him?
How dare you do that to Mason?!
よくも マイセンを！
キヒャヒャヒャヒャ…
（スレイ）やあっ！
キエーッ！
（スレイ）ううっ
水よ 敵を穿(うが)て！
Water!
Shred my foe!
（ルナール）キエーッ！
ヒャッ！
Sorey, get back!
スレイ 下がって！
（スレイ）やあっ！
（ルナール）チッ
（スレイ）やああっ！
It had no effect?!
効いてないのか？
ジイジ
Gramps!
Away with you, evil being.
去れ 邪悪なる者よ
（ルナール）ああん？
ヘッ お前らに構って―
I shouldn't be snacking, anyway.
Not when the main course is getting away.
メインディッシュを逃すのは
面白くない
I'm so sorry, Gramps.
（スレイ）ごめん ジイジ
（ジイジ）うん？
I brought a human to Elysia, and now that thing...
俺が 人間をイズチまで
連れてきちゃったから―
あんなやつが
それは違う！
You've got it all wrong!
It's not your fault or hers that the hellion appeared.
あの憑魔のことは
君のせいでも―
まして 彼女のせいでもない！
（ジイジ）
ミクリオの言うとおりじゃ
Mikleo is right.
（スレイ）ジイジ
Gramps...
Perhaps keeping that girl away might have prevented that hellion from entering this realm.
（ジイジ）確かに
あの娘を遠ざけておけば―
邪悪な者が
この地に入り込むことは―
なかったのかもしれん
じゃが それは 自分たちさえ
平和であれば よいという―
But it would've been selfish for us to believe that only our safety mattered.
身勝手な考えでもある
Our peace is connected to the outside world too.
この地の平穏は
外の世界とも関係している
それを無視するようなことは
あってはならんのじゃ
We must not turn a blind eye to that.
あいつ…
What did he want?
メインディッシュを逃すのは
面白くない
Not when the main course is getting away.
He didn't appear here just because a human came to Elysia.
あいつが ここに現れたのは―
人間が イズチに
入ったからじゃなくて―
アリーシャを狙って！？
He was going after Alisha!
They'll probably freak out with me gone suddenly.
（スレイ）黙って行って
驚くだろうな
Sorry, everyone!
みんな ごめん！
Okay!
よし！
（ミクリオ）何が？
（スレイ）おっ…
Oh?
Whoa! Mikleo?!
ミクリオ どうして！
抜け駆けなんてさせないさ
Thought I'd let you duck out of here?
I'm going too.
僕も行く
Seriously?
ミクリオ
あのキツネ男の言葉
From what the fox man said, it's fair to assume that he's after Alisha.
狙いは アリーシャと
考えるのが 自然だ
You picked up on that too, huh?
（スレイ）
ミクリオも気づいたんだ
当然
Of course.
Look.
見てくれ
What's this?
これは？
僕は ジイジに
言われて―
Gramps asked me to go out and search the ruins and find some clues about that girl.
遺跡で アリーシャの
手がかりを探していたんだ
This is the crest of Hyland.
ハイランド王家の紋章だ
アリーシャ･ディフダ
I don't think this "Alisha"
is any ordinary knight.
ただの騎士では
ないようだね
Consider it a clue to finding Alisha in Ladylake.
これを手がかりに―
レディレイクで
アリーシャを捜そう
どうせ 君は
何の考えもなく…
You're probably clueless about...
どうせ 君は
何の考えもなく…
（スレイ）ミクリオ！
Mikleo!
I'm so happy you're coming with me!
来てくれて
すげえうれしい！
ウソ１つ
つけない君じゃ―
I couldn't let you navigate the
world of humans alone.
人間の中では―
Not as guileless as you are.
やっていけない
だろうからね
I bet Gramps is mad, though.
（スレイ）
ジイジ 怒ってるよな
He has a message, actually.
（ミクリオ）
ジイジから伝言
〝自由に
自らの思う道を生きよ〞
"Walk the path you believe in and live your life to the fullest, and I know you will not go astray."
〝お前の人生を精一杯〞
だってさ
これが 世界！
This is really it!
This is our world!
Next Time
Sorey
So this is where the legendary Lady of the Lake lives! Look at all the people!
Indeed, it's impressive.
Mikleo
Sorey
Someone's going to pull out the Sacred Blade
and become the Shepherd. I wonder what
he'll be like.
Maybe they'll be like Gramps. Someone dignified, with the solemn air of a sage.
Mikleo
Sorey
But the Shepherd could also be a girl, like Alisha.
Hm, but still... I think it'll be someone who has the right mind and body to face the hellions.
Mikleo
Sorey
I guess so.
In any case, it certainly won't be you, Sorey.
Mikleo
Sorey
Oh, come on! I have a chance too!
No way.
Mikleo
Sorey
Oh, yeah? What'll you do if I do become the Shepherd?
Let's see... I'll make you all the snacks you could want.
Mikleo
Sorey
Nope, that's not enough to mend my broken heart.
Then what?
Mikleo
Sorey
Make funny faces throughout next week's preview.
What?!
Mikleo
Sorey
Next week: "Mikleo's Funny Face."
Don't miss it!
Mikleo
No! It's "The Sacred Blade Festival"!